"Disrespecting the fire moth"
不敬火蛾
"brings disaster from above."
祸从天降
This phrase
这一句
also conceals a threat.
隐藏的应该也是威胁
If we persist in our investigation
我们若继续坚持调查
and prevent them from causing chaos,
阻止他们作乱
you and your loved ones
那么你和你的亲友
might face unforeseen calamities.
可能会有飞来横祸
How could you say such things to my lady?
你怎么能和夫人说这些
Are you deliberately
你这不成心
causing her distress?
让夫人担忧吗
With her intellect, it's only a matter
以她的才智
of time before she figures this out.
猜到这一层是迟早的事
- I... - I merely gave her a heads-up
我 我只是提早
in advance.
给她提了个醒
What's the matter?
怎么了
Did you see a healer?
看过郎中了吗
I'm perfectly fine.
我没事
Thank you for your concern.
多谢关心
Don't overexert yourself.
别强撑
That will cause me to worry.
我会担心的
You must stay safe.
你可不能有事
Otherwise,
要不然
who prepares medicinal dishes for me?
谁给我做食补药膳
Shen Du.
沈渡
I just can't muster the strength
我今日真的没有力气
to bicker with you today.
同你斗嘴
Alright then.
好
I misspoke just now.
刚才是我说错话了
What's really bothering you?
你到底怎么了
Shen Du,
沈渡
I have a passion for investigation.
我喜欢查案
I'm passionate about the quest for truth,
我可以忘我地追逐真相
but I prefer to keep my family out of it.
却不想牵连我的家人
The Fire Moth Sect communicated with
他们火蛾门
me through the messages on the corpses.
用尸体上的字向我传声
They have meticulously planned everything
他们早就计划好了一切
and intentionally staged a show for us.
故意给我们演戏呢
They're demonstrating their power to us.
他们在向我们示威
This is a warning!
这是警告
You fear that if you continue,
你是怕继续查下去
it may endanger your family.
会牵连到你的家人
When we were in Xiang'an,
在襄安的时候
if we hadn't arrived in time,
若非我们及时赶到
Caiwei and Mr. Han
三姐他们
would have already lost their lives.
早已没有了性命
If...
若是
If they really are targeting
若我在营州的时候
my family
他们真的
while I am in Yingzhou,
对我的家人下手
what would I do?
那该怎么办
How can I shield them
山高路远
from harm when I'm so distant?
我该如何护他们周全
I pondered for four hours,
我思来想去两个时辰
and I truly have no solution.
我真的没有任何办法
If you wish,
如果你愿意的话
I can arrange a carriage to take you back.
我派车送你回襄安
As for the business in here,
营州的事情
you need not worry about it.
你就别管了
What about you?
那你呢
Can you carry on without me?
你怎么办
Me?
我
Does my lady wish
夫人难道是想
for me to personally
让为夫亲自
escort you back home?
送夫人回娘家
We cannot return.
我们不能回去
You're the commander of the Imperial Guard.
你是内卫府的大阁领
I'm an archivist.
我是刑部令史
We are on a
我们此行
crucial mission.
是有任务的
I knew it.
我就知道
You would never leave.
你是绝对不会走的
A fleeting emotion won't diminish
一时的情绪
your enthusiasm for investigation.
不会影响你查案的热情
Don't act like
你别装作
you understand me so well.
你好像很了解我的样子
Have you regained your composure?
回过神来了
This is the Yan Xing I know,
这才是我认识的颜幸
sharp-tongued and unyielding.
牙尖嘴利 不留情面
Of course,
当然了
you are not intimidated by authority and
也不畏强权
have the tenacity to face challenges head-on.
有着偏向虎山行的执拗
I...
我
I know you are concerned
我知道你在担心
about your family's safety.
你家人的安危
I, Shen Du, assure you
我沈渡向你保证
that the things you fear
你担心的事情
will absolutely not come to pass.
绝对不会发生
Before coming to Gannan,
来甘南道之前
I made contingency plans.
我留了后手
As it stands,
目前来看
everything is well under control.
一切都在掌握之中
Do you still remember
还记不记得
that letter from Xiang'an?
那封襄安来的信
An urgent letter from Xiang'an?
襄安急信
Who sent it?
是谁寄来的
Lady Xu.
徐内司
Of course I remember.
我当然记得
During the Garment Bestowal Festival(Garment Festival\Day),
每年授衣节的时候
The Great Grandmother, every year,
太皇太后
would go to
都会去
the Lishan Hot Springs Retreat
骊山温泉山庄休养
and would reward some officials' families
还会嘉赏一些臣子家眷
to accompany her.
随行休沐
The letter from Lady Xu informed me
徐内司来信是告诉我
that the members of the Yan Family
已经将颜府的人
have been included on the list.
安排进了随行名单
Within Her Majesty'
在太皇太后的
line of sight,
视线范围之内
I believe no faction
我想任凭哪派
would dare to act recklessly.
都不敢造次
Why didn't you tell me, Shen Du!
好你个沈渡
However,
不过话说回来啊
there is indeed one thing
现在的确是有一件
that may not seem urgent,
不是那么重要
but nonetheless,
但是不管怎么说
it is connected to you.
都与你有所关联的事
What is it?
何事
Regarding that headless corpse case,
那个无头尸案
the suspect's brother-in-law,
嫌犯的妹夫
Ji Dafu, has shown up.
纪大福来了
This Ji Dafu
这个纪大福呢
has a rather unique background.
身份十分特殊
The deceased and the suspect
死者和嫌犯
are both the elder brother of his wife.
都是他妻子的亲哥哥
Please, my lord,
求求您给草民
I am begging you here.
一条生路吧 行吗
When will my brother-in-law's case
我那舅子那案
be closed?
什么时候才能结
I can accept that
这人头找不到
the head is missing,
我认了
but can we
咱能不能
allow the body to be buried soon?
让尸身早点入土为安啊
Ji Dafu,
纪大福
please remain calm.
你稍安勿躁
This case is still under investigation.
此案尚在调查之中
Lord Mo,
莫刺史
are you looking for me?
你找我
I heard you have some new suggestions
听说你对此案
regarding this case?
有些新的建议
There are some anomalies in this case
此案有些异象
that I am still investigating.
我还在调查之中
My suggestion is to investigate
我的建议是
this case alongside the
将此案与新娘一案
bride abduction case.
并案调查
If we combine the cases,
若是并案
the investigation duration
这查案的时长
will likely be extended,
就会进一步拖长
and that could mean...
那恐怕
Mr. Pan,
潘郎君
what do you mean by that?
什么意思
I see you, the so-called top detective,
我看你这第一神探
are all name and no game!
是浪得虚名啊
What's with your rule
还立个什么
of never meeting the employer?
从不与雇主照面的规矩
I think you are just
我看你就是
afraid of failing
怕事情办不成
and embarrassing yourself!
丢脸罢了
Today,
今日
let's do this in front of Lord Mo;
咱们就当着莫大人的面
just give me a straight answer:
你给我个痛快话
Can you solve the case and catch
五日之内能不能结案
the murderer within five days?
抓到凶手啊
If you can't catch him,
若是抓不到
return my money
就把钱退给我
so I can find someone else!
我好另觅高人
If the case cannot be solved,
若是结不了案
I will refund the money for sure,
我自会退钱
but I am already
但我已经
close to identifying the murderer.
快查到凶手是谁了
Who is the murderer?
凶手是谁
The murderer is
凶手就是
the masked specter.
半面鬼
To avoid refunding,
你的那个朋友
your friend
为了不退钱
threw out the ghost theory.
抛出的鬼神论
It actually worked.
还真奏效
Upon hearing that, Ji Dafu
那个纪大福听完之后
was visibly shocked and took his leave.
大惊失色然后就告辞了
However, Lord Mo
但莫刺史那边
was not so easy to deceive.
可就没那么好忽悠了
Mr. Pan,
潘郎君
I have submitted the bride abduction case
新娘案我已经上报刑部
to the Ministry of Justice for closure.
做结案处理
Lord Mo,
莫刺史
I have provided a new statement.
潘某提供了新的笔录
I have reviewed it.
我看过了
So why is it being closed so hastily?
那为何如此潦草结案
Xu Jize has new testimony, which could
许己则有了新的证词
potentially lead to a lighter sentence.
或能轻判
The eyeless corpse reveals a hidden plot
无眼尸一看就是案中案
and is linked to the headless corpse case.
和无头尸案颇有勾连
Mr. Pan,
潘郎君
this is not Xiang'an!
这里不是襄安
The Yingzhou has been
是曾经
embroiled in conflict for decades.
深陷兵祸几十年的营州
The situation in here is precarious.
营州局势不稳
Although we've established provincial
我朝虽设都府
governance, Xichen eyes our lands with ambition.
然西辰虎视眈眈
Historically, it has been
历史上
invaded by Xichen numerous times.
更是多次被西辰侵占
To quell the unrest in the Western Regions
欲平西域之乱
and prevent the resurgence of war,
防战火再起
we must unite the hearts of the people.
在于凝聚民心
But do you know what
然而凝聚民心
is essential to achieve that?
你可知靠的是什么
Please enlighten me, my lord.
潘某愿闻其详
What is essential
靠的
is long-term stability.
是长治久安
It requires severe punishment to
是以严苛律法杜绝罪恶
eradicate evil, to solve every case,
有案必破
and to apprehend every criminal.
有贼必抓
It's essential to instill in people
需要让人相信
the belief that as long as the officials
只要大苍的官员
are on duty,
在任一天
the Yingzhou
营州
will be a place where the citizens
就是一座可以让百姓
can live their lives in peace.
安心度日的城池
Thus,
所以
strict laws must be enforced.
乱世就要用重典
Xu Jize's head is
许己则的头颅
destined to be displayed on the city wall,
注定要被挂在城楼上
serving as a
成为那颗
dreadful warning to others, correct?
震慑人心的人头是吗
Scummy was utterly wicked,
二赖皮穷凶极恶
his death is of no consequence
死不足惜
and does not require investigation.
亦不必查
Xu Jize perpetrated
许己则
the violation of a married woman.
强奸有夫之妇
His guilt is amplified to a higher degree.
罪加一等
He has violated border laws,
破坏边塞律法
so he can't escape the death penalty.
死罪难逃
However, I can assure you
不过我可以答应你
that he will die peacefully
让他安稳去死
and his head will not be
不必成为那颗
displayed on the city wall.
挂在城楼上的人头
You have shared this
你将这件事
with me in such detail
这么详细地讲给我听
not merely to highlight how embarrassing
绝不止是为了告诉我
it was for Pan Chi today, right?
潘驰今日有多丢脸吧
You want to convey to me
你是想告诉我
the importance of understanding Lord Mo,
要多理解莫刺史
who was intervening in the case
插手案件
and was eager to bring it to a close.
急于结案的举动
His position means
他的位置
he can't pursue the truth of the case
注定不能同我们一样
with the same unwavering focus as we do.
一心只追求案件的真相
You are reminding me
你在提醒我
to be more empathetic towards
要多多注意
Lord Mo's circumstances
莫刺史的处境
and not to doubt
不能怀疑
his genuine concern for the people.
他有一颗爱民之心
What I want to convey to you
我是想告诉你
is that people are inherently complex
人是很复杂的
and we shouldn't rush to conclusions.
不能那么快下结论
Shen Du.
沈渡
How much do you
你对莫谦之
trust Mo Qianzhi?
有多信任
He used to be the one I trusted the most.
他原来是我最相信的人
And what about now?
如今呢
Now...
如今
he is the one I most wish to trust.
是我私心最想信任的人
To uncover the truth,
凡是要查明真相
one must inevitably navigate
都难免要经历
the very process you are experiencing now.
你现在的过程
Regardless of how trivial the detail,
再小的细节也罢
or how familiar the person,
再亲近的人也好
first, do not shy away from doubt,
首先不要去怕怀疑
and have the courage to verify everything.
要敢于去证实它们
Trust
信任
can also serve as
也可能
a powerful tool in investigation!
也是一种追查的力量
The Fire Moth Sect has deeply infiltrated Yingzhou.
火蛾门在营州渗透深远
Shen is closely tied to Mo.
沈与莫关系密切
- Leave now! - Please, take another look!
走走走 再看一眼
Get out!
走
- Just one more time. - Go away!
再看一眼吧 走走走
Enough!
别说了别说了
- Piss off! - Read it once more!
走 你再看一眼
Just leave!
快走快走快走
Excuse me,
店家
bring me another pot of wine!
再给我来壶酒
Alright!
好嘞
Yan Xing?
颜幸
Why are you here?
你怎么在这儿
Take a look!
看一看
Please, have a look.
客官 看一看
These are quite trendy!
都是新上的样式
Xing,
六娘
what are you doing here?
你来这儿做什么
I...
我
came to take a stroll with the pigeon.
来遛鸽子
Take a stroll with the pigeon?
遛鸽子
Xing,
六娘
do you realize
你可知
that the specialty of this eatery
这家店的招牌
is roasted pigeon?
就是烤乳鸽
But on that note,
不过这话说回来
isn't it a bit cruel
你这么做
to treat your pigeon
是不是对这鸽子
this way?
也太残忍了
Letting it witness
让它自己亲眼看到
its own grim fate.
自己这必死的命运
This drink
这一杯
is dedicated to that poor pigeon.
就敬这只可怜的鸽子
You're not here to drown
你不会是因为
your sorrows
今天下午
after being criticized by Ji Dafu
被纪大福编排无能
this afternoon, are you?
在这儿借酒消愁吧
Good news travels slowly,
果然是好事不出门
but bad news spreads like wildfire.
坏事传千里
To me, Ji Dafu
这纪大福在我眼里
is insignificant.
什么都不是
His words
他的话
are not worth my attention.
还入不了我潘驰的耳
Then you are drinking because...
那是因为
the case is closed?
结案
I heard you received new testimony
听说新娘案
regarding the bride abduction case.
你拿到了新的证词
Any findings?
可有什么发现
Findings?
发现
There are no new findings,
哪有什么新的发现
just some irrelevant testimonies.
都是些无用的证词罢了
However,
不过
to collect evidence,
我为了搜集那些证据
I went to the prison to see Xu Jize.
我去牢房里找了许己则
After questioning him,
在问了他的话之后
as I was about to leave,
我要走的时候
he suddenly said to me...
他突然对我说
Mr. Pan!
潘郎君
You are also an educated
你也是个
man from a humble background, right?
寒门的读书人吧
With your courage and eloquence,
以你的胆识谈吐
why aren't you serving as an official
却不在刑部为官
but instead working as a lowly
而是做个劳什子
civilian detective?
民间神探
Let me take a wild guess,
我大胆猜一下啊
you and I are of the same kind,
你跟我是一类人
burdened by our lowly origins!
受累于出身卑寒
Please, don't shut me out!
求你别关门
My poetry has been
我的诗文
submitted to my lord for over a month.
已经呈交府上一月有余
I wonder if my lord has read it?
不知黄阁老看过了没有
What a persistent stray dog!
真是赶不走的野狗
With that shabby appearance,
就那穷酸样
he still expects my lord to recommend him?
还想让我们郎君保荐
We are not the same type of people.
我和你道不同
No matter how much I resent it,
我虽有再多不甘
I would never stoop
也做不出
to vent my frustrations on the weak!
向弱者泄愤的事情
The weak?
弱者
No,
不
I never bully the weak!
我从不欺凌弱小的
I target
我欺凌的是
those who have always
那些一直
oppressed and humiliated the humble,
打压欺辱寒门的
the gentry families!
名门世族
They were born to sit in high positions
他们生来就能坐至公卿
and treat us humble folks
把我们这些寒门
as their servants.
当作仆隶
I have indeed defiled their bride,
我是染指了他们的新娘
and I want them to experience
我就是想让他们尝尝
the bitter sensation of humiliation.
屈辱的滋味
This sensation
这种滋味
is something we humble folks have endured
我们寒门庶士百年来
for generations.
每一天都在苦咽
Now that it has come to this,
事已至此
do you still not see your wrongdoing?
你还不觉得自己有错
I do!
有
In the case of Lady Du, I admit
在杜娘子的案子里
I made a mistake by not being observant!
我犯了不察之错
The so-called lack of observation refers
所谓不察
to the fact that when you were about to
是指作案刚开始发现
abduct her, you found out the Lis were
李家甚至
not even considered to be gentry, right?
连士族都称不上对吗
Indeed, you are quite the detective!
果然是第一神探
After Lady Du was kidnapped,
杜娘子被绑出去以后
scummy claimed that
二赖皮说
the Li Family is a wealthy household.
李家是大富之家
They built their wealth from
最早呢是由李鸿发
small businesses founded by Li Hongfa.
做小生意发家致富的
However, he was determined
但是他一心
to have his son enter the officialdom,
想让儿子入仕
and because
就因着
he was a merchant *The lowest social status in ancient China
是士农工商里的商
Li Zimo, like me, later
所以李子墨跟我一样
had Li Hongfa spend a large sum of money
后来李鸿发花了大价钱
to erase his past and assume
给自己洗白成了一个
a false identity as a gentry.
士族之后的假身份
Li Zimo
李子墨
was then able to take the exams.
后来就可以报考了
So you ultimately decided
所以你最后决定
to cease your criminal activities
停止作案
and began arguing with scummy?
便和二赖皮开始了争吵
Yes,
对
we had quite a heated argument!
我们吵得可厉害了
Later, I realized that we seemed
后来发现
to be tailed, prompting us to stop.
好像被人跟踪了才作罢
But throughout this ordeal,
但我从始至终
my intention was always to return her
我一直想给杜娘子
to her rightful place.
送回去的
I didn't see a murder case coming.
结果谁知道遇到了命案
I'm not the one that killed scummy!
二赖皮真不是我杀的
I
杜小婉
returned Du Xiaowan in one piece.
我也几乎完璧归赵了
I will honestly report everything
今日你所说
you stated
我会如实上报
for the sake of sentencing.
以作量刑参考
If we adhere to the law, it could
若以律法
indeed result in a lighter sentence.
确实可以轻判一二
But to me,
但在我的心里
you are nothing but
你就是个
a complete coward!
不折不扣的懦夫
The wrath of the valiant
勇者愤怒
is directed at the strong;
利刃向更强者
the wrath of the craven
怯者愤怒
is directed at the weak.
利刃向更弱者
You lack the courage to confront
那些真正打压你的豪强
your true oppressors,
你不敢动
yet you prey upon
却把目光投向了
helpless women.
手无缚鸡之力的弱女子
This isn't revenge;
你这不是报复
you're merely a petty coward who
你不过就是个
bullies the kind and fears the wicked.
欺善怕恶的小人而已
Sentencing?
量刑
That has long been decided!
早就结束了
I am doomed to die!
我必死无疑
Since you just arrived in here,
你们刚来营州啊
you don't understand this Lord Mo.
不了解这个莫刺史
Since the first day of my imprisonment,
我从我来的那一天起
I've never expected to get out alive.
我就没打算活着出去
You are right.
你说得对
I brought this upon myself,
我是自作自受
digging my own grave.
自掘坟墓
No, I shouldn't
不
have been born into this world.
我就不该生在这个世上
In my next life,
下辈子
I would rather be an
我宁愿生作一个
illiterate farmer
不识字的庄稼汉
than a
也不做一个
mediocre
似懂非懂的
bookworm.
读书人
You should stop drinking.
你别喝了
Hey,
店家
don't serve him any more wine.
别再给他上酒了
Bring him a bowl of lamb noodle.
给他来一碗羊肉汤面
Alrighty!
行 好嘞
Here, please.
来 您请
The lamb from the Gannan region
甘南道地区的羊肉
is a renowned delicacy.
可是出了名地好吃
Trust me.
你信我
Instead of seeking escape in alcohol,
与其借酒消愁
let a bowl of soup be your comfort.
不如借一碗汤面消愁
Give it a try!
试试
How is it?
如何
The flavor is indeed delightful!
这味道确实不错
See? I didn't lie to you.
看吧 我没骗你吧
"Laughing to the heavens, I depart,"
仰天大笑去
"Striding across the divine land."
高步踏神州
"The noble may hold themselves high,"
贵者虽自贵
"To me, they're but dust in the wind."
吾视若尘埃
"The humble may see themselves low,"
贱者虽自贱
"Yet who can deny their worth?"
谁言不千钧
"Shaking off the dust, I survey the mountains,"
振衣览群山
"Washing my feet in the long river."
濯足于长河
Xing,
六娘
why are you suddenly reciting this?
你突然背这个做什么
I just feel that
我只是觉得
this poetry is bold and grand.
这檄文豪迈大气
In just a few strokes, it reveals
寥寥几笔就揭露了
the oppression of the humble.
打压寒门之实
What a delightfully biting critique!
好不痛快
Once this piece was published,
此文一出
it spread throughout the capital.
传遍了皇城茶楼酒肆
Even in those days,
甚至在那些日子
the young gentry of Xiang'an City
襄安城里的士族子弟
were cautious not to flaunt their status
出门吃饭的时候
when dining out, for fear of stirring
都不敢太过张扬
the undercurrents of public discontent.
怕惹上暗潮涌动的民怨
You've set the stage so thoroughly,
你这铺垫这么多
surely it's not merely to
不会只是为了
flatter my literary skills, right?
夸我的文采好吧
Of course not.
当然不止
I also want to commend you:
我还要夸赞
I truly admire your courage.
我钦佩你的勇气
As long as one maintains the
人只要永远保有
bravery to challenge decaying authority,
迎击腐朽权威的勇气
sometimes a single phrase
有的时候一句话
or a piece of poetry
或者一篇诗文
can wield immense power.
都能拥有很大的力量
I understand
我知道
the current plight of humble families
大苍现下寒门的处境
may leave you feeling disheartened.
会令你感到失望
But as long as we
但只要我们
refuse to lose hope,
人人都不放弃
I believe there will come a day
我相信总会有
when the talented from humble origins
为寒门才子
honorably embrace their
拨开乌云见青天的
rightful future.
那一日
I can't quite tell if it's
不知道
because the noodle is remarkably delicious
是这碗面太好吃了
or if your words
还是你的话
have truly inspired me.
起到了激励作用
I now feel rejuvenated
我现在感觉是神清气爽
and could take on ten more cases!
还能再查十个案子
No, stop,
别别别
we should avoid having
甘南道的案子
more cases in Gannan.
可不能再多了
At this moment,
现下
we've already reached the point that
已经查到
there's no time for a break.
没有时间休息了
If there're more on the way,
案子再多
I truly can't keep going like this.
可真的就撑不下去了
There's something
有件事
I'd like you to know.
我还是想告诉你
If you are facing any abuse,
你若是受暴
you don't have to tolerate it.
不用忍受
Who says that
谁说
the residence of The White Death
这白无常府
is a place you can enter but not escape?
是入得出不得
In my view, Shen Du is
依我看
not as intimidating as he appears to be.
这沈渡就是个纸老虎
Just say the word,
只要你一句话
and I, Pan Chi, will gladly
潘驰我定是为你
confront him for you and
上刀山下火海
help you break free from your troubles.
帮你脱离苦海
Wait, are you misunderstanding something?
你 你是不是误会了
No one is abusing me.
没有人对我施暴
If no one is abusing you,
没人对你施暴
then how did you get
你这额头上的伤
that lump on your forehead?
是怎么来的
Every time I see you, there's
每每见你
always a new bruise alongside an old one.
一处新伤一处旧伤的
Or is it from somewhere else?
难不成不是在家里伤的
I got it at home indeed.
确实是在家里伤的
How can I explain this to you?
我怎么跟你解释呢
In short,
总之
Shen Du truly hasn't mistreated me.
沈渡真的没有欺负我
Although marrying into the Shen Family
虽然我替嫁入沈府
is somewhat absurd, this
有一些荒唐
marriage is not what he desired either.
也并非他所愿
But overall,
但总体上
Shen Du is a decent husband.
沈渡算是个合格的夫君
He genuinely cares
他对我和家人
for me and my family.
也多有照拂
Moreover,
而且
I will eventually part ways with him.
我早晚都是会离开他的
Whether it's Shen Du
无论是沈渡
or myself,
还是我
we both understand
都心知肚明
that day is approaching.
这一天很快就要到来
Why is that?
为何
Because in his heart,
因为他心里
there has always been someone else,
始终都有一个人
and that person is not me.
而那个人不是我
The role of his wife
这个位置
was never truly meant for me.
本来就不是属于我的
My lady,
夫人
Lord Mo appreciates your busy schedule
莫刺史感念您公务繁忙
and has specially arranged for you
特意安排您
to visit the renowned Yixi Pool in
去营州最知名的汤池
Yingzhou for some relaxation.
忆汐池休沐
Fair lady,
小娘子
our Yixi Pool is just
咱们忆汐池
as good as the royal Lishan hot springs.
可不比皇家骊山温泉差
It draws from the
是西岭山引下的
millennium waters of Xiling Mountain,
千年之水
enhanced by natural geothermal heat.
辅以天然地热
The pool is infused with
池中更是添加了
dozens of fragrant herbs.
数十种香料
It boosts vitality for men,
男能温肾补阳
and enhances beauty for women.
女能美容养颜
Its benefits are well-known.
功效那是有口皆碑
Couples seeking offsprings
甘南道方圆百里
from all around Gannan region
求子的夫妻
often come here
都会特意来这池中
to soak.
泡一泡
Thank you for the detailed explanation.
多谢讲解
You must be exhausted guiding me,
您一路引导辛苦了
so please leave and take a break.
先去歇着吧
Oh, no, no,
不成不成
I haven't even help you
奴婢还没
into your silk dress yet!
伺候您穿纱衣呢
Who is it?
谁
Me.
是我
Why are you here?
你怎么来了
I'm here to
自然是
enjoy the hot spring.
来泡汤
This is for women only!
这里是女汤池
You should go to another spot.
你去别的地方泡
The Yixi Pool is just one pool,
忆汐池就一个池
No separation between men and women.
哪分什么男女
Besides, Lord Mo arranged
何况营州府安排
for us to soak together as a couple.
我们夫妇一块泡汤
If we were to soak separately,
若是分开泡
wouldn't that seem odd?
会不会太奇怪了
What would those people outside think?
让外面那些人怎么看
There are people outside?
外面那些人
There are a few maids and servants
外面有几个仆妇和家丁
waiting outside.
在看着
Even if it's just for appearances,
即便是做戏
I should soak with you.
也得和你一块泡
I'm coming in now.
我下来了
Wait, wait!
等一下等一下
Don't get in just yet!
你先别下来
Turn around
你背过身去
and close your eyes.
把眼睛闭上
Are you feeling shy
你害羞了
and hesitant to soak with me?
不敢和我一起泡
I'm not shy at all!
我才不是呢
I'm just worried you might be fidgety
我是怕你扭扭捏捏
and make things awkward for me.
到时候让我尴尬
Alright, you can open your eyes now.
好了 可以睁眼了
Come on in.
下来吧
Now I can't see anything at all.
现在我什么也看不到了
Where do I step down from?
从哪儿下来
Oh no,
糟了
his eyesight isn't great.
他眼睛不好
I should have left a candle for him.
早知道给他留一盏
I could have blown it out after he got in.
等他下来了再吹的
Just wait a moment,
你等着
Let me help you.
我来扶你
You mentioned that in my heart
你说我心里
there has always been someone.
一直有一个人
Who is that person?
那个人是谁
Mo Xiuxiu?
莫绣绣
No, I can't answer this.
不行
That would reveal that I was eavesdropping
那不就暴露了我偷听
on his conversation with Mo Qianzhi.
他和莫谦之说话了吗
Shen Du,
沈渡
why were you eavesdropping on me?
你怎么窃听我啊
Can't you
你就不能
just ask me directly?
光明正大地问吗
If I ask now,
我现在问
would you dare to answer?
你敢回答吗
Of course I would!
我当然敢啊
I've always heard
素来听闻
My lord is known for disinterest in women,
大阁领有不近女色之名
and I wholeheartedly concur with this.
这一点我深以为然
Within the Shen residence,
沈府里
there are hardly any concubines,
别说是通房妾室
let alone maids,
便是女婢都很少
Add to that
再加上
your constant displeasure with me;
你对我多番看不顺眼
doesn't that say it all?
这还不能说明问题吗
I avoid women
我不近女色
because I already have
是因为心里已经有了
someone I hold dear in my heart.
喜欢的女孩子
So I misunderstood, then?
那就是我误会了呗
I met her
我与她
when we were children.
年幼相识
I still treasure the
她的藤编小猪
little woven pig she made.
我收藏至今
Because of her,
因为她
I managed to survive
我才可以在罪容所里面
in that dark place.
苟活下来
Indeed,
是了
thanks to Xiuxiu's brother pleading for mercy,
多亏莫绣绣她哥求情
he was spared execution
他才免了死罪
and sent to the Custodial Ward instead.
进了罪容所
Every night,
每每入夜的时候
she would quietly slip into the garden
她就会悄悄潜入后花园
to bring me comfort and food.
给我带来慰问和吃食
In those dark days,
暗无天地的日子里
that was the light
那是我每晚
I eagerly awaited each night.
苦苦守候的光
I didn't even know
我甚至不知道
her name
她姓甚名谁
nor had I ever seen her face clearly.
也不曾看清过她的面庞
The only gift I ever gave her
而我送给她唯一的礼物
was a copper whistle.
只是一只铜哨
This whistle was a gift from my father.
这哨子是我爹送我的
I remember her telling me once
我记得她跟我说过
that one day
有一天
she'd take me out openly and with dignity.
会光明正大地接我出去
One day,
总有一天
I'll help the Shen Family clear your name
我会帮沈家翻案
and take you out openly and with dignity.
光明正大地接你出去
Years passed,
后来很多年
and I never saw her again.
我都没有再见过她
It was as if she had vanished.
她像人间蒸发了一般
Until one day,
直到有一天
as if it were fate,
就如同命中注定一般
she became my wife.
成为了我的妻子
But the ironic part is,
但可笑的是
at that time,
当时我
I had no clue she was
根本不知道她就是
the girl I had cherished in my memories.
我记忆中的那个女孩
Eventually, I learned the truth,
后来我知道了
and I hope it's not too late.
希望不算太晚
I want to let her know
我想告诉她
that in my heart,
在我心里
from the very beginning,
从始至终
the one has always been her.
一直都是她
-I... -You...
我 你
-You... -I...
你 我
You go first.
你先说
How did you know
你怎么知道
that rattan pig was made by me?
那个藤编小猪是我编的
You've been
你这一路上
pondering for so long
犹豫了这么久
just to ask this?
就问这个
I've known from the very start
我从一开始就知道
that it wasn't Xiuxiu who made it.
不是绣绣编的
You're so talented!
你好厉害
I want to weave one
我也想编个
for Du as a birthday gift.
给阿渡哥哥当生辰礼物
But no matter how hard I try
可是我怎么编
it still turns out to be ugly.
都编得很丑
Can we
你
trade?
能不能和我换一下
Of course, take it!
好 你拿去吧
Thank you!
谢谢
You are so nice!
你人真好
On my birthday,
我生辰那天
I received that little pig.
收到了小猪
I had originally intended to find a way
原本想寻个由头
to express my gratitude to you.
和你道谢
But then I learned your family took you.
却得知你被家人接走了
At that time, I was still wrapped up in
当时我还满心沉浸在
the joy of knowing my father
我爹没有不要我的
hadn't abandoned me.
幸福里
He was just a bit late due to his duties.
他因为公差来得迟了些
I didn't pay attention to my surroundings.
我也不曾注意到旁的
I never expected that
没想到
you had kept the rattan pig all along.
你还一直留着藤编小猪
Later on,
后来
the Shen Family was raided.
沈家就被抄家了
That rattan pig
这个藤编小猪
became one of the few belongings
成了为数不多
I could hold onto.
可以留下来的东西
So I kept it close to my heart.
我也就一直留着
It also reminds me of
也能让我想起
the cherished moments when
我父亲教我藤编的
my father taught me weaving.
那些好时光
It wasn't until recently that I discovered
直到前不久我才知道
you are actually the same girl.
此六娘是颜六娘
The Custodial Ward...
罪容所
You promised you'd come to get me,
你一直说要来接我
but why did you stop showing up?
怎么后来没有来
Because
因为
I crawled in through the dog hole
我是从后花园的狗洞里
in the garden.
爬进来的
Later, they discovered
后来他们发现了
that hole
这个漏洞
and patched it up.
就把狗洞给堵上了
After that,
再后来
you didn't even need me to free you.
你也不用我来接了
Thank you.
谢谢
You still came to lead me home.
你还是来接我回家了